只要你有路子 就几乎能给任何东西上保险
You can insure almost anything, if you know the right people.
可以给喜欢的球队投保 可以怕被绑架而投保
You can insure your fantasy football team, or your own kidnapping.
可以给天气投保 可以给高尔夫一杆进洞投保
You can insure the weather, or the cash prize for your hole in one contest.
澳大利亚板球运动员Merv Hughes为他的胡子投保了775,000美元
Australian cricket player Merv Hughes insured his mustache for $775,000,
《伸展台计划》的主持人Heidi Klum为她的双腿投保了两百万美元
and Project Runway's Heidi Klum had her legs insured for $2 million—
你以为是每条腿一百万?
not $1 million each, by the way;
错啦 劳埃德保险社给她右腿签下的保额比左腿高一点点
Lloyd's of London actually determined that her right leg is slightly more valuable than her left leg.
可这跟月薪三千的我又有什么关系呢?
Did you need to know that? No, but I needed to tell you.
给一条腿上保险可能有点难度
Now, insuring a leg might be tricky,
但如果你想知道地球上最复杂的保险政策——
but if you're looking for some of the most complicated insurance policies in the world—
或者说地球以外——
or just slightly outside of the world—
那肯定是卫星的保险了
look no further than satellites.
要了解如何为像卫星这样小众而昂贵的东西投保
To understand how exactly you might go about insuring something as niche and expensive as a satellite,
我们首先需要了解保险是如何运作的
we need to talk about how insurance works in the first place.
你需要知道的关于保险公司的第一件事是——
The first thing you need to know about insurance companies—
希望我不是最先发现的——赚钱
and I hate to be the one to break this to you—is that their job is to make money.
为了保证自己赔出去的钱不超过赚到的
And in order to make sure that they're not forking over more money than they're raking in,
保险公司需要准确评估所有出售的保单被索赔的可能性
these companies need to accurately assess the likelihood that any given policy they've sold will be claimed.
这一过程称为"核保"
This is done with a process called "underwriting",
保险公司将对其承保的任何东西建立一个统计模型
where an insurance company will create a statistical model of whatever it is that they're insuring—
无论是车 房子 Heidi Klum的两条腿
your car, your home, your pair of Heidi Klum's legs—
并确定该东西在投保期间遭遇意外的可能性
and determine the chance that that thing will be destroyed during the time that it's covered.
我们以人寿保险为例
So, let's just take life insurance as an example:
核保人的工作就是计算你的死亡概率
an underwriter's job will be to figure out the chance that you're gonna die
通过了解被保险人的年龄 性别 身高 体重 血压 胆固醇 病史
by looking at stuff like your age, gender, height, weight, blood pressure, cholesterol, medical history,
吸烟习惯 职业选择 驾驶记录 国外旅行史
smoking habits, career choice, driving records, history of foreign travel,
以及是否喜欢在周五晚上和朋友玩俄罗斯轮盘赌
and whether or not your hobbies include playing Russian roulette with your friends every Friday evening.
核保人会把客户的风险分为四类
This lets them put you in one of four categories of risk,
要是"Preferred Plus" 就说明你是全世界最健康的人
with "Preferred Plus" meaning that you're one of the healthiest people on Earth,
"Standard" 则是在很委婉告诉你和死亡好像有那么一点点近
and "Standard" being a very polite way of highlighting your special relationship with mortality.
卖人寿保险其实没那么复杂 毕竟人还是比较好预测的
Now, selling life insurance isn't all that complicated, because people are pretty predictable,
特别是手里有上百万人的平均情况时
especially when you're taking the average of thousands or millions of them.
相关数据都有 建模简单
The relevant data is accessible, easy to model,
即使最坏的情况发生 赔付也不会带来多大亏损
and if worse comes to worse, the payouts don't hurt that badly
因为人命的赔付额并不高
because people just aren't worth very much.
但这一切到了卫星就全变了
None of these things are true when it comes to satellites,
这也是为什么给卫星投保是个高风险的活
and that's why insuring them is such a risky task—
实际上 有好几年赔付额远远超过了保费
in fact, there have been plenty of years where insurers lost way more than they made
因为这些计算真的太难进行了
because these calculations are just so difficult to pull off.
不过如果想知道他们如何尽力不赔钱的 那么可以接着往下看
But if you were wondering how they at least attempt to not lose money, here's how it works.
一颗卫星的生命周期全程都会涉及各种保险
Each stage of the satellite's life is covered by a different kind of insurance policy,
每一款都是针对卫星在该阶段可能面临的特定风险
each geared to the particular risks that the satellite might face during that period.
首先是"发射前保险"
The first is pre-launch insurance,
覆盖了从卫星离开制造设施起 到点火后几秒钟的时间
which covers the satellite between the time that it leaves the manufacturing facility,
all the way up until a few seconds after ignition;
这与任何其他需要安全运到佛罗里达的昂贵物体的保险没什么不同
this isn't all that different from insuring any other hugely expensive object
that needs to be transported to Florida without being destroyed beyond repair,
所以我们来看接下来有意思的地方: 发射保险
so let's move on to where things get interesting: launch insurance.
发射保险保障卫星的生效期非常短暂 但非常关键
Launch insurance covers the satellite for a very brief, but very crucial period of time,
从发射无法终止时开始生效
kicking in as soon as the launch can no longer be aborted,
到卫星在太空成功与火箭分离时为止
up until the point that the satellite has successfully detached from the launch vehicle in space.
这种风险类型的计算几乎是不可能做到准确的
Calculating the risks for this type of coverage is almost impossible to do accurately—
大部分取决于运载火箭自身的可靠性
most of this hinges on the reliability of the launch vehicle itself,
还会有烦人的《国际武器贸易条例》(ITAR)搅局
but uh oh, here come the International Traffic in Arms Regulations to ruin everyone's fun again:
实际上 用来将卫星送上太空的火箭
it turns out that the rockets we use to send satellites to space
与用来将致命武器送到阿富汗的婚礼上的火箭非常相似
are awfully similar to the rockets we use to send deadly explosives to Afghani weddings,
所以这些数据大部分都是保密的
so most of this data is kept secret;
很少有保险公司能够获得特定运载火箭的具体信息
very few insurers are ever given access to the specifics of a given launch vehicle,
即使有 通常也要与美国签署一份同意法令
and when they are, they usually have to sign a consent decree with the United States
允许他们在签合同后的几年里在该公司的办公地点派驻政府监督员
allowing them to station government overseers around the clock in the company's offices
for years after the fact.
保险公司往往只能搜集公共领域中的有限信息
Insurers are often left with whatever limited information is in the public domain,
而这些信息很难为数十亿美元的保险合同背书
and that information usually isn't the best basis for a multi-billion-dollar insurance contract.
比如举个例子 核保员可能网上一查 发现
Just as an example, they might be dealing with statistics like this:
这款火箭当前发射成功率是零
a rocket that technically has a 100% failure rate.
但又不能真给一个百分百失败的火箭签保单
Since they can't actually issue an insurance policy with a 100% chance of failure,
所以就只能盲猜一个
they just have to take a stab in the dark.
而且这一切还是建立在核保人知晓卫星要由哪款火箭发射的情况下
And that's assuming that they know what the launch vehicle even is—
有时 卫星投保的时候发射的火箭还没选好
sometimes, these contracts are written before a launch vehicle has been chosen,
那么核保人只能盲猜这颗卫星会由哪枚火箭来打
so the underwriters literally just try to guess what rocket might get used
然后祈祷千万别是那款百分百失败的火箭
and cross their fingers that it's not one of the ones with a 100% failure rate.
星箭分离后 卫星开始独立运行 新的保险就来了: 在轨保险
Now, once the satellite is on its own, a new kind of insurance kicks in: in-orbit insurance.
和发射保险类似 这个阶段的保险也很难准确核保
Much like launch insurance, this is not an easy phase to accurately underwrite.
一般来说 保险公司会查看使用同一平台的卫星
Generally, insurance companies will look at satellites built on the same bus—
平台其实就是支撑卫星有效载荷的地方
which is just a fancy word for this thing—
查看类似载荷的卫星 看看它们平均寿命如何
with similar payloads, and see how long their average lifespans were.
保险公司还会对仍在轨运行的卫星进行模拟
They'll also do simulations of satellites that are still in orbit,
尝试计算这些卫星的失效时间
try to calculate when those satellites will fail,
并使用这些数据预测那些还未发射的卫星
and then use that data to make predictions for satellites that have yet to be launched.
为了准确地进行这些预测
To accurately make those predictions,
他们必须考虑到诸如辐射 温度的剧烈波动 随机的太阳风暴
they've gotta factor in things like radiation, crazy temperature fluctuations, random solar storms,
以及伊龙·马斯克一高兴就打上去玩的东西
and any miscellaneous objects that Elon Musk sent up there for fun.
最后一点实际上是在轨保险的保费最近一直在飙升的原因
That last point is actually why this kind of insurance has been skyrocketing recently,
因为保险公司担心卫星相撞的概率越来越高
as insurers are getting more and more worried that satellites are going to start crashing into one another,
造成空间碎片的连锁反应 损坏轨道上大量的通信系统
creating a cascading effect of debris that will disrupt many of our critical communications systems
让地球被太空垃圾包围~
and trap humanity on Earth forever.
不过几年内应该还不会发生
But we still have a few years until that happens,
所以还是老老实实在B站看我的视频玩吧
so just keep spending your time watching YouTube videos about how niche insurance policies work.
接下来是恰饭 不翻了
If you want to have slightly more time to watch YouTube videos about how niche insurance policies work,
while also managing to eat delicious, healthy, home-cooked meals at a reasonable cost,
then boy do I have a solution for you.
In fact, it's the exact solution I personally found to be able to watch more YouTube videos
about how niche insurance policies work
while also managing to eat delicious, healthy, home-cooked meals at a reasonable cost a few years ago,
before they even became our sponsor, and it's called… Hello Fresh.
The concept is pretty simple: you select which meals you want on their app,
then the next week, an insulated box shows up on your doorstep
with all the ingredients you need to make those meals already measured out and prepped
so you can skip straight to the fun part of cooking.
So, usually in thirty minutes or less, you have something with home-cooked quality,
but you didn't have to plan your meals out, you didn't have to waste time at the grocery store,
and you didn't have to waste time prepping ingredients as much.
I've been using HelloFresh since 2020 and have these hundreds of recipe cards to prove it,
making delicious meals like this Tropical Teriyaki pork bowl,
and have really appreciated how it unlocks more free time
without having to compromise on expensive delivery food or unhealthy frozen meals.
If you'd like to try them out, go to HelloFresh.com
and use code HAI21 for 21 free meals plus free shipping.